Henri Goiran Papers MS049
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Henri Goiran Papers
1943 -- 1960
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Goiran, Henri Jean Joseph Auguste
MS049
21.6 Linear Feet 32 boxes
Arrangement
The collection was processed at some point prior to the mid-1980s, but the system of organization is unclear.
Custodial History
This collection was donated to Tufts in 1976 by Henri Goiran's son, Roger. here is no other information available regarding the provenance of the papers; we failed to discover any connection between Henri or Roger Goiran and Tufts University.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains materials related to Goiran's research and teaching, including journals and notebooks, 1943-1953; lectures, 1943-1959; manuscripts of "Europe at the Beginning of World War II," "French in America," and "French in New York," and "French Folklore Society," as well as related research material and clippings; and research notes on on Courrier de Etats Unis and L'Europe Nouvelle.
Biographical / Historical
Henri Jean Joseph Auguste Goiran was born on June 9, 1881 in Toulouse, France. He was the son of Madeleine and General Francois Louis Auguste Goiran, French Minister of War in 1911 and Mayor of Nice from 1912-1919. Henri Goiran attended the École de la Droit et Faculté des Letters de Paris, earning degrees in law and political science. In 1907, Goiran began his diplomatic career with his appointment to the French Consulate in New York City. Goiran was appointed Consul to Liverpool in 1919, was appointed Consul General to South Africa in 1924, and from 1930 to 1933 he served as Consul General in London. He was then appointed Minister Plenipotentiary in Mexico for six years. In 1939 Goiran became the French Ambassador to the Baltic States in Riga, Latvia; he remained in this position until his retirement in 1940.
After 1940, Goiran's career shifted towards teaching and writing. From 1946-60, he served on the faculties of Fordham University, the French University of New York (Columbia University), and the New School for Social Research in New York. Goiran's writing and research focused on history and he continually published in journals and magazines. Active with the French Folklore Society of New York, Goiran served as president of the organization for several years.
Goiran's decorations include the Légion d'Honneur, the Croix de Guerre (1914-18), the Grand-Croix de l'Ordre Azteque, and the Silver Medal for Acts of Courage. He married Lucie Chouanard in 1937 and they had one son, Roger.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. This collection may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.
Henri Jean Joseph Auguste Goiran; Foreign affairs; Diplomats
- Additional accessions, 1943 -- 1960; MS049.001; 21.6 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes Goiran's journals and notebooks, 1943-1953; lectures, 1943-1959; manuscripts of "Europe at the Beginning of World War II," "French in America," and "French in New York," and "French Folklore Society," as well as related research material and clippings; and research notes on on Courrier de Etats Unis and L'Europe Nouvelle.
  Arrangement
  This series is not arranged.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Journals, Notebooks, 1945 -- 1953; MS049-001 (Box data_value_missing_3178e0f1a8c566b265bc0f2867a65bc1, Box 1)
    Former barcode 39090011482466g.
  - Journals, Notebooks, 1943 -- 1945; MS049-002 (Box data_value_missing_3178e0f1a8c566b265bc0f2867a65bc1, Box 2)
    Former barcode 39090011482474g.
  - Lectures, 1943 -- 1950; MS049-003 (Box data_value_missing_6259232d3ab378a3abc92b7606970868, Box 3)
    Former barcode 39090011482482g.
  - Lectures, 1950 -- 1954; MS049-004 (Box data_value_missing_6259232d3ab378a3abc92b7606970868, Box 4)
    Former barcode 39090011482490g
  - Lectures, 1954 -- 1956; MS049-005 (Box data_value_missing_6259232d3ab378a3abc92b7606970868, Box 5)
    Former barcode 39090011482508g
  - Lectures, 1956 -- 1959; MS049-006 (Box data_value_missing_6259232d3ab378a3abc92b7606970868, Box 6)
    Former barcode 39090011482516g
  - "Europe at the Beginning of World War II" - Manuscripts, MS049-007 (Box data_value_missing_6259232d3ab378a3abc92b7606970868, Box 7)
    Former barcode 39090011482524g.
  - Manuscripts - Europe at the Beginning of World War II, European Affairs, MS049-008 (Box data_value_missing_6259232d3ab378a3abc92b7606970868, Box 8)
    Former barcode 39090011482532g.
  - Manuscript - Europe at the Beginning of World War II, MS049-009 (Box data_value_missing_6259232d3ab378a3abc92b7606970868, Box 9)
    Former barcode 39090011482540g.
  - Lectures and Manuscript - French in America, MS049-010 (Box data_value_missing_b96ee9c4865c733b4920ff60a4eadedf, Box 10)
    Former barcode 39090011482557g.
  - Manuscript - French in America, MS049-011 (Box data_value_missing_b96ee9c4865c733b4920ff60a4eadedf, Box 11)
    Former barcode 39090011482565g.
  - Manuscript - French in America, French in New York, MS049-012 (Box data_value_missing_b96ee9c4865c733b4920ff60a4eadedf, Box 12)
    Former barcode 39090011482573g.
  - Manuscript - French in New York, MS049-013 (Box data_value_missing_b96ee9c4865c733b4920ff60a4eadedf, Box 13)
    Former barcode 39090011482581g.
  - Manuscript - French in New York, MS049-014 (Box data_value_missing_b96ee9c4865c733b4920ff60a4eadedf, Box 14)
    Former barcode 3909001482599g.
  - Materials on French and American Relations, MS049-015 (Box data_value_missing_b96ee9c4865c733b4920ff60a4eadedf, Box 15)
    Former barcode 39090011482649g.
  - Material on Folklore, MS049-016 (Box data_value_missing_b96ee9c4865c733b4920ff60a4eadedf, Box 16)
    Former barcode 39090011482656g.
  - Material on French Folklore Society, MS049-017 (Box data_value_missing_bc0091d77e9c61e799d408a5c44ae941, Box 17)
    Former barcode 39090011482664g.
  - Material on French in Mexico, MS049-018 (Box data_value_missing_bc0091d77e9c61e799d408a5c44ae941, Box 18)
    Former barcode 39090011482672g.
  - Various Subjects, MS049-019 (Box data_value_missing_bc0091d77e9c61e799d408a5c44ae941, Box 19)
    Former barcode 39090011482680g.
  - Material Relating to French History, MS049-020 (Box data_value_missing_bc0091d77e9c61e799d408a5c44ae941, Box 20)
    Former barcode 39090011482698g.
  - Misc. Clippings, MS049-021 (Box data_value_missing_bc0091d77e9c61e799d408a5c44ae941, Box 21)
    Former barcode 39090011482706g.
  - Mexico - Notes and Manuscript, MS049-022 (Box data_value_missing_bc0091d77e9c61e799d408a5c44ae941, Box 22)
    Former barcode 39090011482714g.
  - Misc. Printed Material and Clippings, MS049-023 (Box data_value_missing_bc0091d77e9c61e799d408a5c44ae941, Box 23)
    Former barcode 39090011482722g.
  - Misc. Clippings, MS049-024 (Box data_value_missing_601372ee6050e99261ed112d487315b3, Box 24)
    Former barcode 39090011482730g.
  - Notes and Lectures, 1959 -- 1960; MS049-025 (Box data_value_missing_601372ee6050e99261ed112d487315b3, Box 25)
    Former barcode 39090011482748g.
  - Notes - France in Mexico - Documents 1827-78, MS049-026 (Box data_value_missing_601372ee6050e99261ed112d487315b3, Box 26)
    Former barcode 39090011482755g.
  - Research Notes, Books, and Articles, 1907-52 - International Affairs, MS049-027 (Box data_value_missing_601372ee6050e99261ed112d487315b3, Box 27)
    Former barcode 39090011482763g.
  - Personal Material - Notebooks and Journals, MS049-028 (Box data_value_missing_601372ee6050e99261ed112d487315b3, Box 28)
    Former barcode 39090011482771g.
  - Research Notes on Courrier de Etats Unis, 1828-1908, MS049-029 (Box data_value_missing_601372ee6050e99261ed112d487315b3, Box 29)
    Former barcode 39090011482789g.
  - Research Notes on Courrier de Etats Unis, 1908-36, L'Europe Nouquelle, 1922-33, MS049-030 (Box data_value_missing_601372ee6050e99261ed112d487315b3, Box 30)
    Former barcode 39090011482797g.
  - Research Notes on Foreign Affairs, Revue de Deux Mondes, Luno; Books and Articles, MS049-031 (Box data_value_missing_ce64662cf04bbc2baabf3e112b542184, Box 31)
    Former barcode 39090011482805g.
  - Research Notes - L'Europe Nouvelle, 1934-36; Hitler; Books on America; Misc., MS049-032 (Box data_value_missing_ce64662cf04bbc2baabf3e112b542184, Box 32)
    Former barcode 39090011482813g.